A Guide to the Page County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1813-1914 (bulk 1831-1914)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Page County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1813-1914 (bulk 1831-1914)
The Library of Virginia
Page County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1813-001-1914-012
Digital images
Page County (Va.) Circuit Court
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Digital images were generated by PTFS through the Library of Virginia's Circuit Court Records Preservation Program.
Historical Information
Chancery causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case.
Page County was named according to most sources, for John Page, revolutionary patriot, congressman, and governor of Virginia from 1802 to 1805. It was formed from Rockingham and Shenandoah counties in 1831.
Scope and Content
Page County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1813-1914 (bulk 1831-1914), are indexed into the Chancery Records Index. Cases are identified by style of suit consisting of plaintiff and defendant names. Surnames of others involved in a suit, including secondary plaintiffs and defendants, witnesses, deponents and affiants, and family members with surnames different from the plaintiff or defendant are indexed. Chancery causes often involved the following: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, divorces, debt, and business disputes. Predominant documents found in chancery causes include bills (plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, wills, slave records, business records or vital statistics, among other items. Plats, if present, are noted, as are wills from localities with an incomplete record of wills or localities other than the one being indexed.
Chancery causes are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history.
Arrangement
Organized by case, of which each is assigned a unique index number comprised of the earliest year found in case and a sequentially increasing 3-digit number assigned by the processor as cases for that year are found. Arranged chronologically.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Page County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia. See A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm
See The Chancery Records Index to find the chancery records of additional Virginia localities.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Page County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Subjects:
African Americans--History.; Business enterprises--Virginia--Page County.; Debt--Virginia--Page County.; Divorce suits--Virginia--Page County.; Estates (Law)--Virginia--Page County.; Equity--Virginia--Page County.; Land subdivision--Virginia--Page County.
Geographical Names:
Page County (Va.)--History.; Page County (Va.)--Genealogy.
Genre and Form Terms:
Chancery causes--Virginia--Page County.; Deeds--Virginia--Page County.; Judicial records--Virginia--Page County.; Land records--Virginia--Page County.; Local government records--Virginia--Page County.; Plats--Virginia--Page County.; Wills--Virginia--Page County.
Selected Suits of Interest
- 1832-001 Isaac Overall v. Widow of George Hetick, etc.:
  Involves issuing a Scire Facias to repeal a letter patent or grant on grounds that is was obtained by false suggestion. Plaintiff filed a Land Office Treasury Warrant for 4,790 acres prior to defendant. George Hetick filed his Land Office Treasury Warrant for 25,517 acres and plaintiff's patent was contained within his lands. Lands in question were originally part of Shenandoah County (now Page.) According to county surveyor in an 1833 deposition, his home was burnt down and plaintiff's plat and survey were recorded in a previous surveyor's book that was in his home and was burnt in the fire. Part of defendant's claim rests on the fact that he was a lifelong resident of Pennsylvania.
- 1832-008 George Kite and wife v. Nancy Painter, etc.:
  Cause involves a contract dispute but cause does not contain any contracts. Suit 1833-007 contains all contracts mentioned. In dispute are the deeds 1823 and 1831 made between Henry Long and his step daughter, Nancy Painter and her son, Adam Painter. Plaintiff's wife was the half sister of Henry Long. Henry Long was said to be old, infirm and a drinker but others surmise that he had fallen under the influence of his step daughter. In a disputed matter, deeds were made by the defendants to Henry Long's sons to convey western lands-320 acres in Ohio and 160 acres in Indiana. These lands in Ohio belonged to Henry Long and his step daughter and her son. Henry Long's kin lived in Rockingham County, Virginia and Ohio. George Kite was said to have bought a family of negroes from Henry Long. Others say that Kite's legacy was paid in slaves by Henry Long. Defendant lived in Shenandoah and Rockingham counties. SEE ALSO 1837-002 and 1839-008.
- 1833-008 Exr of Raphael Conn v. Mary J. Conn, etc.:
  In his will, filed in Page County in 1831, Raphael Conn emancipated all of his 17 slaves. The court rules that his slaves may be hired out or sold to pay for his estate's debts while the legacy of his niece, Mary J. Conn, is protected-thus increasing his debts. All of this is not lost on his enslaved as they are named defendants along with his niece to the suit. In their answer, they fight back stating that "their liberty should be place on a higher footing than the legacy of his niece which is so far a special legacy." They ask the court to release them from their servitude. They were instead hired out and his estate earned $185.00 However, the estate remained $600.00 in debt. Cause mentions his valuable enslaved. SEE ALSO 1834-007.
- 1838-011 John Beaver and wife, etc. v. Heirs of Isaac Strickler:
  Cause begins in Shenandoah County with an appeal regarding the improper estate division of Isaac Strickler. Cause involves extensive land holdings-over 3,000 acres. Cause contains 7 plats, a contract and detailed commissioner's reports. Numerous tracts of land are mentioned including the River tract, Sheets farm, Cherry Orchard lot, Spring Farm lot, Beaver and Williams tracts, Apple Orchard farm, the Hill tract, the Hite tract, the Saw Mill tract and the School House lot. Part of Stickler's property included 2 land grants from Virginia governor's William H. Cabell and James Monroe-totaling 590 acres. Isaac Strickler's son, Jacob, served in the Army in Canada.
- 1838-012 Admr of Samuel Coffman, etc. v. Pierson Judd
  Cause involves a contract dispute centering around the land grant of Robert Oliver of Baltimore, then deeded to Thomas Shirley of Madison County involving 42,700 acres of land in the counties of Madison, Culpepper (now Rappahannock County) and Shenandoah (now Page County.) Cause contains 5 plats, deeds and numerous references to Land Treasury Warrants-Nos. 5650, 1401, 429, 3023 and Warrants from the Virginia Land Office-Nos. 1079-1096, 139-140, 1161-1164. Complainant cannot make a good title to land sold and defendant prays that contract may be rescinded.
- 1843-004 Dr. Beverly R. Welford, creditor, etc v. Nicholas W. Yager, trustee, etc.:
  Cause involves plaintiffs who live in Spotsylvania County and City of Richmond hiring out slaves to the business of Benjamin Blackford and Son.] Benjamin Blackford and his son ran a manufacturing and casting iron business responsible for the operation of the Isabella Furnace and Speedwell Forge in Page County and the Caroline Furnance in Shenandoah County. Through deeds of trust, defendants Yager and Kendrick are given full power and authority to supervise and control the operations of said furnaces and forge-the catch, they are also responsible for the company's debts. Creditors reside in Page, Shenandoah, Rockingham, Frederick, Rappahannock, Warren and Monroe counties in Virginia and Baltimore, Maryland (for a complete list see deed on page 210 of the CRI.) The cause was originally heard with cause 1843-005.
- 1850-006 Heirs of Isaac Bundy, etc. v. Mary Richardson, etc.:
  Isaac Bundy is identified as a free colored man. His heirs are identified as bastard free negroes as is his common law wife. Isaac and his wife were childless. Isaac's brothers and sisters did not recognize his common law wife-however the court did for legal purposes. His wife, Frances, in turn disputed whether those coming forward were the legitimate heirs to Isaac.
- 1852-004 Thomas M. Almond v. Ambrose Booton, trst, etc.:
  Contains certain church property in town of Luray with meeting house and school house. Property was once part of Shenandoah County. Plaintiff is a member of Mount Caramel Baptist Church. Defendant is a trustee of the Hawksbill Baptist Church. The Hawksbill Baptist Church becomes the Mount Caramel Baptist Church-known as the Old School Baptists. Plaintiff buys church property and proceeds are shared by the Old School Baptist Church-one half, the New School Baptist Church-3/10 and the Methodist Episcopal-1/5.
- 1854-009 Emanuel Grove v. Peter B. Borst and David McKay
  Plaintiff claims that there was a verbal agreement to go to Greene County and bid in partnership with the defendants for the first 14 miles of the Rockingham Turnpike Road from Stanardsville to Harrisonburg. Plaintiff relates that the defendants refused to consider your plaintiff as one of the said firm and denied him the principle of participating in the profits of said contracts. Defendants countered saying that there was no agreement and no partnership. Plaintiff was a merchant in town of Luray. Defendants had been contractors and partners on various Public Works. Enslaved were hired to help build the road--a very arduous job considering the mountainous terrain.
- 1856-010 D and H Forrer] v. Richards Bros and Co], etc.:
  Daniel Forrer, plaintiff, resides in Augusta County. Daniel and Henry Forrer were owners of Shenandoah Iron Works.] The iron works was comprised of 30-40,000 acres in Page and Rockingham counties. These lands contained immense beds of valuable ore. Property of iron works consisted of a furnance, forge, merchant and chopping mills and 2 saw mills. Before end of 1854, the Forrers had sold half of property, real and personal, to Thomas S. Richard and James Moore of Pennsylvania. By August 1855, Richards and Moore] had purchased entire establishment. However, a contract was never signed by parties. A later contract between Forrer and Richards was lost or left behind in Baltimore. One of the defendants, James B. Eastham moved to Texas. He owned enslaved individuals. Those enslaved named in suit were hired to work at the Iron works. SEE ALSO 1867-017.
- 1858-012 Harrison Jones, etc. v. Admr of Wharton Jones, etc.:
  Wharton Jones was a guardian, administrator of 2 estates, a commissioner who sold slaves and an executor of an estate. Jones' varied activities and the fact that he kept no written accounts placed a great burden on his administrator. The administrator had to search through immense number of papers and various records in Shenandoah and Page counties, get information from individuals in order to enable him to do justice to others and to prevent immense losses to Jones estate. All the commissions and profits of these various settlements went to the benefit of Wharton Jones' estate. Depositions give detailed information on Wharton Jones clientele as well as those of other estate administrators. Genealogical information on Wharton Jones' heirs is also included. Heirs also reside in North Carolina and Missouri. Jones' administrator resides in Bedford County, Virginia.